Guide to the Alex Bittelman Papers TAM.062
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Alex Bittelman Papers
1930-1972
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Bittelman, Alex, 1890-1982
Bittelman, Mrs. Alex
Gordon, Max
TAM.062
4.25 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Alex Bittelman, Communist activist and theoretician, was one of the founders of the Jewish Communist movement in the United States. He joined the Communist Party in 1919 and held a number of responsible positions until his expulsion in 1959. The collection consists of manuscripts, clippings and off-prints of various unpublished and published writings, including the book-length "The Bolshevik Revolution and its Historic Consequences," manuscripts of Communist Party USA programmatic and internal discussion documents, correspondence relating to Bittelman's writings, correspondence between Bittelman and William Z. Foster (some in relation to Bittelman's assistance to Foster in his writing endeavors), legal documents relating to Bittelman's indictment under the Smith Act and to the U.S. government's attempt to deport him. Some of the material is in Yiddish, including clippings reviewing Bittelman's writings. Topics include Communism and the Jewish people, Marxist theory, and political economy.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Max Gordon in the early 1950's; an additional accession was purchased from Alex Bittelman's widow, Mrs. Hittelman (whose first name could not be identified), in 1983. The accession number associated with the gift and purchase is 1983.007.
An autobiographical typescript titled "Things I Have Learned" was donated by Alex Bittelman in 1974. The accession number associated with this gift is 1974.003.
Materials found in repository were added to collection in 2014. The accession number associated with these materials is 2014.158.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Alex Bittelman, Communist activist and theoretician, was one of the founders of the Jewish Communist movement in the United States. Born in the Ukraine, Bittelman was active in the Jewish Labor Bund before emigrating to the U.S. in 1912, where he joined the Socialist Party. In 1919 he helped lead the left wing of the SP into the newly established Communist Party, and became secretary of its Jewish Section. He became closely associated with William Z. Foster throughout his Party career until his expulsion in 1959. After prosecution and attempted deportation (as he was not a U.S. citizen) under the Smith Act, he served three years in federal prison. For many years he wrote the "Questions and Answers" column for the Daily Worker and the "Review of the Month" column for the Party's theoretical magazine, The Communist(later Political Affairs). He served as a member of the Party's Political Bureau at various times.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of manuscripts, clippings and off-prints of various unpublished and published writings, including the book-length "The Bolshevik Revolution and its Historic Consequences," manuscripts of Communist Party USA programmatic and internal discussion documents, as well as writings by others. The collection also contains clippings, correspondence and notes, in Yiddish, relating to Bittelman's writing for the Morning Freiheit, the Communist Party's Yiddish-language newspaper. An unpublished typescript titled "Things I Have Learned" describes Bittleman's childhood and radical activities in Russia; his arrival in the United States in 1912; the formation of the American Communist Party; comments on its important personalities including Earl Browder, William Z. Foster, Jay Lovestone, Charles E. Ruthenberg and many others; his reflections on the New Deal and Cold War, and concern for Jewish survival.
Correspondence in the collection relates to Bittelman's writings and political activity, including correspondence between Bittelman and William Z. Foster, some in relation to Bittelman's assistance to Foster in his writing endeavors. Legal documents relate to Bittelman's indictment under the Smith Act, and to the U.S. government's attempt to deport him.
Topics of particular interest to Bittelman include Communism and the Jewish people, Marxist theory, and political economy.
Note: In the Box and Folder List some item-level contents lists received with the 1983 donation of material have been included.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically within each series.
The files are grouped into five series:
Missing Title
I, Writings, Articles and Notes, 1931-1971
II, Communist Party Documents, 1942-1971
III, Correspondence, 1944-1972
IV, Legal Papers, 1950-1969
V, Typescripts, Undated
Communism -- United States.; Jews |x Identity.; Right and left (Political science).; Clippings (information artifacts); Jewish communists -- United States.; Manuscripts; Marxian economics; Autobiographies.; Soviet Union -- Description and travel.; Correspondence.; Political prisoners |z Ukraine |z Kherson (Ukraine).; Legal documents.; Ruthenberg, Charles E. (Charles Emil), 1882-1927; Foster, William Z., 1881-1961; Browder, Earl, 1891-1973; Lovestone, Jay.; Communist Party of the United States of America; Bittelman, Alex, 1890-1982; Bittelman, Mrs. Alex; Gordon, Max
- Series I: Writings, Articles and Notes, 1931-1971
  - Clippings: Discussion Bulletin (Communist Political Association Publication), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings: Life Magazine- "Khrushchev Remembers", 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings: Morning Freiheit- Articles about Bittelman (In Yiddish), 1950, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings: Morning Freiheit- Articles by Bittelman (In Yiddish), 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings: Morning Freiheit- Articles by Others (In Yiddish), 1945-1946, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings: New York Times, 1965, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: New York Times, 1968, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings: Pravda, 1948, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings: Der Tog (The Day) - Articles about Bittelman, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clippings: Daily Worker (Includes Article by Bittelman, "The Political Source of our Theoretical Errors"), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings: Daily World, Notes, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Morning Freiheit: General, [1945] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Russian Publications ( Communist, Novoe Vremya), 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Writings: "A Dialogue on Marxist Theory"/ "The Study of Jewish Life…"/ "Autobiographical Notes"/ "American Jewry in the Affairs of the Jewish People"/ "The Historic Role of American Labor and its Vanguard Party…"/ "What is the Outlook for the Jewish People?", 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Writings: Typescripts distributed by the Communist Party- "The Two Worlds," "The Negro Problem", 1946 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Writings: "The New State of Israel; The Meaning of the Struggle For Its Existence"/ "Ethics and Politics in World Communism"/ "The Current Struggle in Marxism-Leninism"/ "A Program For a Period" (With a Letter to the National Committee of the CPUSA)/ "What is Marxism-Leninism"/"Reverse Wall Street's Verdict and Prevent the Outlawing of a Working Class Political Party"/ "National Committee Statement Approving the Main Line of Bittelman Report", 1948-1949, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Writings: "War Economy in USSR"/ Wall Street's War Aggressions and the People's Standards of Living"/ "Frederick Engels"/ The Party's Main Line-To the Masses"/ "Amnesty Can Help Peace and Democracy"/ Corruption, Warmongering, and Pro-Fascist Reaction", [1949], 1953 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Writings by Others: Hill, Edward, "American Imperialism and the Roosevelt Foreign Trade Program"/ Karpov, M. M., "On the Philosophical Views of A. Einstein", [1949], 1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Writings in Yiddish (I), undated, 1945, [1951] (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Writings in Yiddish (II), undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Writings, Clippings: "On Magil's Manuscript, 'Communism and Fascism'", 1963-1964, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Writings, Clippings, Notes: "The Communist Party is Indestructible"/ "On the Decision"/ "The Triumphs of Lenin's Teachings"/ "Truman's national Emergency and Our Immediate Tasks"/ "The Party's Main Line Meets Needs of the People"/ Speech to be Delivered at Mass Meeting on Apr. 26, 1953/ "Economic Trends in the U.S."/ "What Is the Working Class and Progressive Answer to the Growing Fear of an Eisenhower Victory?"/ "Armaments and War Stimulated Inflation are Driving Developing Economic Crisis to Catastrophic Crash". Notes: "Articles and Pamphlets"/ Course Outline on Capitalism, 1931, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Writings, Clippings, Notes: Speech- "Strengthen the Fight For Peace"/ "A Reply to a Reply" (Article, Clipping, Correspondence to NY Times)/ "Collaboration or Military Confrontation"/ "America's National Purpose and Goal"/ "The General Political Resolution"/ "Imperialist Reaction Menaces Achievements of Anti-Fascist Victory". Notes: For "July Article"/ "Slogans for November 7th", 1945, 1948, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Writings, Clippings, Notes: Interview with Bittelman/ "Ruthenberg and Foster"/ "Stalin; On his 70th Birthday"/ Speech/ "Questions and Answers"/ "Observations Regarding Document"/ Draft Outline of Book on History of the Communist Party (W.Z. Foster?), 1948-1949, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Writings, Clippings, Notes: "Further Elaboration on Economic Issues and Developments"/ Speech Delivered at Forum, Labor Youth League, 1950, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Writings, Clippings, Notes: "Jerusalem, National Independence, and Peace"/ "The People's Answer to Truman's Economic and Budget Messages"/ "Growing Monopoly, Intensified Labor Exploitation, Truman's 'Welfare'"/ "Who Are the Conspirators?"/ "May Day"/ "Wall Street 'Optimism' and the Developing Crisis"/ "Where is 'Monthly Review Going?"/ "'Monthly Review'-An Estimate"/ "On the Economy"/ "On the Decision". Notes: "The Approaching Economic Crisis and the Program of the C.I.O." (Lecturer's Notes)/ "Five Questions Answered", 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Writings, Clippings, Notes: "A Dialogue With Myself"/ "Statements on the McCarren-Walter Parole Conditions". Handwritten notes, 1946-1953, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Writings, Clippings, Notes: "On the Statements of the Communist Parties Issued by Moscow"/ "Czech Consequences"/ "New Radicalism". Handwritten Notes, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Writings, Notes: "Growing Monopoly, Intensified Labor Exploitation, Truman's 'Welfare'"/ "The Course of the Developing Economic Crisis"/ "Further Elaborations on Economic Issues and Developments"/ The Beginnings of the Economic Crisis in the United States"/ "Combat the War Incitements Against the Soviet Union"/ "New Economic Dangers and How to Meet Them"/ "Truman's National Emergency and Our Immediate Tasks"/ "The Lot of the Working Class Under Capitalism"/ "Memo on Some Questions in the Struggle for Peace"/ "The Truth Is Making Its Way"/ "The Triumphs of Lenin's Teachings"/ "The Deterioration of the Economic Position of the Masses…"/Struggle For the CPSU for Unity of the World Communist Movement", 1946-1953, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Writings, Notes: Page from Play Script. Handwritten Notes, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Greeting card and photographs of Bittelman and others, 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Writings, Notes: "American Jewry in the Affairs of the Jewish People"/ "Winning the Jewish Masses for the Progressive Party"/ "Henry Wallace and 6 Million Jobs"/ "Review of 'Milestones in Stalin's Life'"/ "Jerusalem, National Independence, and Peace"/ "Reverse Wall Street's Verdict and Prevent the Outlawing of A Working Class Political Party"/ "Current Problems in Our Jewish Work". Notes: "Suggestions for Pamphlets"/ "Questions and Answers"/ Handwritten notes on the Economy, [1945], 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Writings, Notes: Series- "The Coalition of the People against the Monopolies", "Labor's Allies in the People's Coalition", "Labor's Fight for Higher Wages and the People's Coalition", "How Do We Fight For Socialism", "Our Party and Leadership"/ "A New Fortress is Rising"/ "A Communist Wage Policy"/ "The Beginning of the Economic Crisis in the U.S."/ "Armaments and Inflation"/ "Nature of the Current Inflation", 1942, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Writings, Notes: "Nature of the Fight Against the Indictments"/ "Amnesty Can Help Peace and Democracy"/ "The Role of War Stimulated Inflation" (Manuscript Excerpt)/ "On the Study of Party History". Notes: "About Last Week's Discussion"/ "On 'A Marxist Theory of Economic Crises", 1942-1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Writings, Notes: "Whither French and Italian Communism". Notes: "On 'A Program for America'"/ "On Report 'On the Present Economic Situation'"/ "Outline Proposals for a Legislative Program", 1949-1950, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Writings, Notes: "Lenin"/ "Current Problems in Our Jewish Work". Notes: Revisions for Unidentified Manuscript/ Lecture Outlines/ Book Outline/ Handwritten noted on the Economy/ Notes on Various Topics, 1949-1950, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Writings, Notes: "Corruption, Warmongering and Pro-Fascist Reaction" (Galley-Proofs for Political Affairs)/ "Articles and Pamphlets" (Reviews)/ "learn the History of the Vanguard American Working Class Party"/ "Lenin's Teachings and World Liberation"/ "Parties and Candidates in the Presidential Elections"/ Speech Delivered at Youth Forum (Labor Youth League), 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Writings, Notes: "Bourgeois Nationalism and Proletarian Internationalism in American Jewish Life Today"/ "Milestones of Stalin's Life"/ "For the Struggle against Positivism and Pragmatism." Notes: On Autobiography, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Writings, Notes: "America's National Purpose and Goal"/ "Analysis of McArthur Hearings"/ "McArthur and the 'Great Debate'"/ "May Day"/ "Role of Science and Society-American Marxists in the Field of Science"/ "American Marxists in the Field of Science and Philosophy", 1951 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Writings, Notes: "On the Overt Acts"/ "The Teachings of Lenin"/ "Comments on 'our Generation Will Not Be Silent'"/ "Questions and Answers"/ "Report on Stalin's 'The Economic Problems of Society'". Notes: "Editorial Errata"/ "How Do you Estimate the White Incident"/ Discussion with W. Z. Foster/ "On the Passage of the 'Outlaw Bill'"/ "Additional Notes on the Passage of the 'Outlaw Bill'"/ Comments on Bittelman's Book on War Economy and Crisis, "Disaster or Wellbeing" (Written by W.Z. Forster), 1951-1954 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Writings, Notes: "The Current Crisis in Marxism-Leninism"/ "On the Statement of the Communist Parties Issued in Moscow in November, 1960" (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series II: Communist Party Documents, 1942-1971
  - Communist Party of the Unites States (CPUSA) Documents: Approval of Bittelman Report on Bourgeois Nationalism by National Committee, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - CUSA Documents: Draft Political Resolution (Presidential Election), 1948 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - CPUSA Documents: Draft Resolution on Political Situation and Task of Party (includes Statement by W.Z. Foster), 1950 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - CPUSA Documents: Draft Resolution ("The Present Situation and the Next Tasks"), 1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - CPUSA Documents: Economic Reports, 1946-1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - CPUSA Documents: Emergency Convention of National Board (Report), Jul 1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - CPUSA Documents: Expulsion of Morris Freedman (Note and Clipping in Yiddish), [1946] (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - CPUSA Documents: Greetings to National Convention, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - CPUSA Documents: Draft Proposals to National Jewish Commission (Includes Comments by John Williamson re: Motions Submitted by Bittelman), 1949, [1950s] (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - CPUSA Documents: Party Anniversaries, 1946, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - CPUSA Documents: Party Program/ Statements Written by Bittelman, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - CPUSA Documents: Report on National Committee Meeting, [1946] (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - CPUSA Documents: Soviet Anniversaries, 1948, 1953, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - CPUSA Documents: Statement to National Committee (W.Z. Foster), 1951 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - CPUSA Documents: Statement to Party, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - CPUSA Documents: Statements Made to National Committee, 1950, 1952-1953, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - CPUSA Documents: Statements Made to the New York State Committee, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - CPUSA Documents: Weekly Reports on War as Soviet Correspondent, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1944-1972
  - Correspondence, 1944-1972 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence (In Yiddish), 1945, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence to Morning Freiheit (In Yiddish), undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence: Open Letters to Central Committee of the CPSU, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence: Open Letters to L. I. Brezhnev (General Secretary, CPSU), 1966, 1968, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence: Open Letters to Members and Leaders of the CPUSA, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence: Open Letters to N. S. Khruschev and Mao Tse-Tung, 1961, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence: Open Letters to Presidents Truman and Johnson, [1947], 1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Open Letter to U.S. Senate and House of Representatives, [1940s] (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Gertrude Ackerman, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with Rudolf and Lily Blum, 1958, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with William Draper, 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with William Z. Foster, 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with J. W. Fulbright, 1963, 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with Walter Neff (Includes Neff's Article "Psychoanalysis and Anti-Semitism"), 1947 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with Publishers and Editors, 1945, 1952, 1962-1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with Robert A. Rosenstone, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Legal Papers, 1950-1969
  - Legal Papers: Correspondence, 1950, [1953], 1966 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Legal Papers: Deportation under Smith Act, Appeals, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Legal Papers: Deportation under Smith Act, Appeals (Others), 1950 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Legal Papers: Deportation under Smith Act, Court Proceedings, [1953] (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Legal Papers: Deportation under Smith Act, Interrogatory, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Legal Papers: Deportation under Smith Act, "On Clear and Present Danger"/ "On Intent", 1952 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Legal Papers: Deportation under Smith Act, Questions and Answers (Mock Interview?), [1950] (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Legal Papers: Deportation under Smith Act, Respondent's Memo in Support of Attorney General's Authority under Internal Security Act, [1950] (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Legal Papers: Deportation under Smith Act, Statements, [1950], 1953 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Legal Papers: Deportation under Smith Act, Testimony, 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Legal Papers: Deportation under Smith Act, Nature of Fight against the Indictments, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Legal Papers: Materials from Prison (Atlanta, Lewisburg), 1957 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Legal Papers: Social Security Cases, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Series V: Typescripts, 1963, undated
  - Typescript: The Bolshevik Revolution and Its Historical Consequences, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Typescript: The Bolshevik Revolution and Its Historical Consequences, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Typescript: The Bolshevik Revolution and Its Historical Consequences- Chapters II, V, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Typescript: A Communist Views America's Future (I), undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Typescript: A Communist Views America's Future (II), undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Typescript: A Communist Views America's Future (III), undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Typescript: A Communist Views America's Future (IV), undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Typescript: Democracy and Dictatorship, Chapters I-V, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Typescript: Democracy and Dictatorship, Chapters II-IX (notes), undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Typescript: Democracy and Dictatorship, Chapters VI,VII, IX, X, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Typescript: Disaster or Wellbeing, Two Lines of Economic Development, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Typescript: Disaster or Wellbeing, Two Lines of Economic Development (Outlines, Insertions, and Reader Comments), undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Typescript: Jewish Survival, a Marxist Outlook, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Typescript: Things I Have Learned, Chapters 1-5, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Typescript: Things I Have Learned, Chapters 6-10, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Typescript: Things I Have Learned, Chapters 11-15, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Typescript: Things I Have Learned, Chapters 16-20, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Typescript: Things I Have Learned, Chapters 21-25, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Typescript: Things I Have Learned, Chapters 26-29, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Typescript: Things I Have Learned, Chapters 30-32, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Typescript: Things I Have Learned (photocopy), Chapters 1-5, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Typescript: Things I Have Learned (photocopy), Chapters 6-10, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Typescript: Things I Have Learned (photocopy), Chapters 11-15, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Typescript: Things I Have Learned (photocopy), Chapters 16-20, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Typescript: Things I Have Learned (photocopy), Chapters 21-25, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Typescript: Things I Have Learned (photocopy), Chapters 26-28, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Typescript: Things I Have Learned (photocopy), Chapters 29-32, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 36)